<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The treasures of the sea A sermon to the mariners upon Deut. XXXIII. xviii, xix. And of Zabulun, he said, Rejoice Zabulun in thy ports, and Issachar in thy tents. They shall call the people unto the mountain, there they shall offer sacrifices of righteousness: for they shall suck of the abundance of the seas, and of treaures hid in the sand.</title>
            <author>Thomson, William, d. 1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62447</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1036A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203769</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825284</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825284</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29662</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62447)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29662)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2156:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The treasures of the sea A sermon to the mariners upon Deut. XXXIII. xviii, xix. And of Zabulun, he said, Rejoice Zabulun in thy ports, and Issachar in thy tents. They shall call the people unto the mountain, there they shall offer sacrifices of righteousness: for they shall suck of the abundance of the seas, and of treaures hid in the sand.</title>
                  <author>Thomson, William, d. 1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Robert Kettlewell, at the Hand and Scepter over against S. Dunstans Church in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXIII. [1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: William Thomson.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Deuteronomy XXXIII, 18-19 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29662:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Treaſures of the Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON TO THE MARINERS UPON</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>DEUT. XXXIII. xviii, xix.</bibl>
               <p>And of Zabulun, he ſaid, Rejoice Zabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lun in thy Ports, and Iſſachar in thy Tents.</p>
               <p>They ſhall call the people unto the mountain, there they ſhall offer Sacrifices of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: For they ſhall ſuck of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Seas, and of Treaſures hid in the Sand.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <l>Terra parùm fuerat: Terris adjecimus undas;</l>
               <l>Fortunae varias auximus arte vias.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Kettlewell,</hi> at the <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Scepter</hi> over againſt S. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleet ſtreet.</hi> M DC LXXXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:29662:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29662:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon was occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally Preach'd upon Mr. <hi>William Harring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton's</hi> (that famous and ſucceſsful Engineer) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the lading out of the <hi>Katherine,</hi> ſunk unfortunately in the <hi>Downs,</hi> many fathoms under Water. The good man therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been proſperous beyond expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in a concern of ſo high a value, <hi>viz. 14000 l.</hi> and upwards, was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to return his thanks to God, and therefore made choice of me to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
<pb facs="tcp:29662:3"/> that Religious Office, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Service of the Church, I did ſolemnly in this following Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Leigh in Eſſex, <date>Nov. 21. 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>William Thomſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29662:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable and Right Reverend Father in GOD, HENRY Lord Biſhop of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SOme Philoſophers tell us, That all the great and goodlieſt Natures diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play their Excellencies in three things, Light, Heat and Love. The more Light dances in Precious Stones, the more is their worth: Heat raiſes Eagles above Worms, and thoſe Palms are held the Nobleſt, which have the moſt Love and Inclination to their Fellows. I need not tell the World how eminent thoſe Qualities are in your Lordſhip, whoſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding daily aſſiſts the beſt Monarch and the beſt
<pb facs="tcp:29662:4"/> Church in the World, with its Lights and Counſels, whoſe vigour and activity of Spirit, mingled with the Nobleneſs of your Blood, has worthily advanced you to the beſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in the Church; and whoſe Candour and Bounty triumphs over ſo many Hearts.</p>
            <p>But it is theſe Virtues, that make all us eſpecially, who have the Happineſs to live under your Lordſhips care, to ſtudy all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ways to give teſtimony of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Duty we owe you. Among the reſt I have put in my Mite, and with your Lordſhips leave, will hereafter endeavour to mend both the coyn and the ſumm. I would not fill your Lordſhips left hand with a Letter, and therefore humbly beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging your Bleſſing, I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Right Honourable and Right Reverend Lord,</salute>
               <dateline>Leigh, <date>Nov. 21. 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Dutiful Son and Servitor, THOMSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29662:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the HONOURABLE GEORGE LEGGE, Eſq; Maſter of the Ordance to his Majeſty CHARLES the Second, &amp;<hi>c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Noble Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Diſcourſe is due to you, upon the account of your favours to Mr. <hi>Harrington:</hi> And therefore as he was pleas'd to make me the Orator of his thanks to God, ſo am I alſo the Meſſenger of his thanks to You. I am a great Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirer of your Honours unſhaken Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and other your great Virtues; and I am as devout a Beedſman for your laſting Proſperity. That there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Heaven may bleſs all that Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb facs="tcp:29662:5"/> Conduct and Integrity, which ſhines ſo gloriouſly in you above moſt others, is the daily Oriſon of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Noble Sir,</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Leigh</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Nov.</hi> 21. 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honours in all Duty and Obſervance, THOMSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29662:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable DANIEL Lord <hi>FINCH,</hi> one of the Lords of His Majeſties Moſt Honourable Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, &amp;<hi>c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Noble Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>YOur many favours oblige me, and your high Concerns in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miralty, encourage me humbly to offer this Diſcourſe, ſuch as it is, at Your Lordſhips feet. I can ſay little of its ſuitableneſs to a Perſon of your great Quality, and leſs of its Worth: But if your Lordſhip ſhall pleaſe to accept of theſe Proluſions, I will hereafter endeavour ſomething more worthly your Lordſhips no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that I may at once give teſtimony of
<pb facs="tcp:29662:6"/> my thankfulneſs for the favours already received, and demonſtrate how much I am,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Noble Patron,</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Leigh</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Nov, 21. 1682.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt obliged Servitor, THOMSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29662:6"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipful SAMUEL HARE Of <hi>LEIGH,</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE daily Experience I have of your Zeal to Religion, your Loyalty to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eſtabliſh'd, and your Kindneſs to me, has emboldened me to preſent the following Sermon to your view, which however imperfect (as the reſt of my Productions) may yet retrieve to your Memory what you have already heard from the Pulpit. There is variety of Inductions from the words, and ſuch as have led us through ſome of the moſt important points of the Chriſtian Faith. It may therefore ſerve at once for a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:29662:7"/> and Syſtem of Religion. Accept it therefore (if not upon theſe accounts, yet) as it is intended for an acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the many obligations by you conferr'd upon,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Good Sir,</salute>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Leigh</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Nov. 21. 1682.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble and obliged Servitor, THOMSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29662:7"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>DEUT. XXXIII. xviii, xix.</bibl>
                  <p>And of <hi>Zabulun</hi> he ſaid, rejoice <hi>Zabulun</hi> in thy going out, and <hi>Iſſachar</hi> in thy Tents.</p>
                  <p>They ſhall call the people unto the mountain, there they ſhall offer Sacrifices of Righteouſneſs: For they ſhall ſuch of the abundance of the Seas, and of Treaſures hid in the Sand.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Owever ſome men, wedded to Cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and Sloth, have declaimed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the dangers and roughneſs of the Sea, looking upon every ſtorm as a Trumpeter of Death, and every Wave as a Winding-ſheet: Yet if we ſhall but ſeriouſly inſpect the nature of the Watry Element, we ſhall find her as calm as any of the reſt, and no leſs advantageous to humane Nature: For whereas the greedy Earth, when ſhe ſhakes, ſpares neither Men nor Cities, and the muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Air inſects us with unhealthful blaſts, and the Fire
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29662:8"/> ſcorches our Blood; Old <hi>Neptune</hi> is of a more tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſpoſition, and if his angry Siſter (<hi>Juno,</hi> the Air) will but let him alone, never fails to be favourable to the concerns of the World. So that <hi>Tertullian,</hi> though in the commendations of other things plentiful enough of words, yet in the praiſe of Water, flows with an Eloquence worthy himſelf and the ſubject, telling us that it is the ancienteſt of all the Elements, and that none of them has ſo many Patronages of Nature, ſo many Priviledges of Grace, ſo many ſolemnities of Diſcipline, nor any ſo highly advanced in the myſteries of Religion. <hi>De Bapt. Thales</hi> aſſerts it the principle of all things; and later Chymiſts aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us that it is productive of whatever the skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Operator pleaſes; that all Art is nothing but an imitation of the great proceſs of God Almighty in the Creation of the World, who having out of nothing call'd a confuſed, (and, as ſeemeth from the Text, a liquid) matter, <hi>the Spirti of God moved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the waters, Gen.</hi> 1. 2. giving motion to the fluid Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all things, who being warmed by that agitation, brought forth the ſucceeding parts of the Univerſe in their Order. Whence <hi>Marius Victor,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Et ſacer extenſis impedens Spiritus undis</l>
               <l>Altrices animabat aquas, dans ſemina rerum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And agreeable hereunto the Stoicks made this Element the food of the Stars, as judging it the part of a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuckle her own Infants; which if ſo, the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the ſtaff of Water, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. 1. may not only prove the diſſolution of the little, but alſo of the greater World.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29662:8"/>
            <p>All Nations from the obſervation of its cleanſing qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity have adopted it into the Ceremonies and Myſteries of their Religion; and the <hi>Platoniſts</hi> have not only made it Purgative here, but Cathartick hereafter, ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing humane Souls to be waſht in the next World from the ſtains they had contracted in this.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Aliis ſub gurgite vaſto</l>
               <l>Infectum eluitur ſcelus.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But it is of infinite advantage to us, that we may be waſht by a more eaſie and purifying Sacrament, when the ſtains of our Nature and the Errours of our Lives are cleanſed by the Waters of Baptiſm, through which ſo many graces of God deſcend upon us as in a ſhower, according to the Prophetick Doctrine of that Ocean of Scripture, and Labyrinth of the Myſteries of God, <hi>Ezek. 36. 25. Then will I ſprinkle clean water upon you, and ye ſhall be clean: from all your filthineſs and from all your Idols will I cleanſe you.</hi> Which though we ſhould interpret with the <hi>Jews,</hi> to ſignifie an abundance of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Bleſſings, increaſed and refreſhed with the dews of Heaven, it could not be diſadvantageous to the Ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Subject: But if with S. <hi>Aug. de doct. Chr. c.</hi> 34. we underſtand it of thoſe many graces, which ſhall, as it were, diſtil through the Holy Font upon the Chriſtian Church, it will much more ennoble this fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſpring of all Vertues, which gave not only bleſſings to the Church, but a Name and Title of Honour to Chriſt himſelf, who, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4. 15. is call'd <hi>a well of living waters.</hi> And truly the ſame Prophet has made uſe of this Symbol, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47. to denote the whole fate of the Chruch, from a beginning ſo ſmall and inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable till Chriſt ſhould <hi>have dominion from Sea to Sea,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29662:9"/> and from the River unto the ends of the Earth, Pſal.</hi> 72. 8. But S. <hi>Gregory</hi> underſtands it of the different degrees and progreſſes of Chriſtian life, waſhing firſt the feet and Epithumetick Organs, and then growing by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of good works and an holy life, till we come to be ſwallowed in the unfathomable Ocean of Divine Contemplations.</p>
            <p>But it is time, after ſo long a Voyage, to make for the Havens of <hi>Zabulun,</hi> to ſurvey the ſtrength of her Ports, and the Riches brought in by the Sea, which were ſo conſiderable, that they were eſteemed a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worthy thoſe who ſhould be the great Preachers and Examples of Religion, who ſhould call the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to the Mountain, to offer the Sacrifices of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</p>
            <p>We will therefore begin with the Hiſtory of theſe two Tribes from the Benediction and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of their great Patriarch <hi>Jacob,</hi> and then proceed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations more practical, and to be deduced from the following words of the Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Rejoyce, O</hi> Zabulun, &amp;c. Gen. 49. 13. Zabulun <hi>ſhall dwell at the Haven of the Sea, and he ſhall be for an Haven of Ships, and his border ſhall be unto</hi> Zidon. So that though he was but the tenth Son, yet is he prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before his Seniors, perhaps for that Chriſt was to be conceived in <hi>Nazareth</hi> of that Tribe. And therefore he has a prerogative, the firſt, which the Holy Text mentions given to man, (<hi>viz. a Dominion over the Fiſh of the Sea, Gen.</hi> 1. 28.) And accordingly his portion was allotted in the <hi>Agrarian</hi> Laws of <hi>Joſhua, Joſh.</hi> 19. 10, 11. And indeed in ſuch a place too, where his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, the <hi>Tyrians</hi> and <hi>Zidonians,</hi> pretended to a chief Admiralty in the Sea, as the firſt Inventors of Navigation. For though a man would think <hi>Adam</hi> could not well
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29662:9"/> exerciſe his jurdiction over his watery Subjects, without the aſſiſtance of ſhipping, and wonder more the world ſhould be ſo dull, that in ſixteen hundred years no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce ſhould be us'd at Sea (eſpecially if it were as well peopled before the Flood, as in the like number of years after;) yet there is no poſitive account of any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val Architecture till the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> who by divine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection prepared his Ark of <hi>Gopher,</hi> againſt the general inundation.</p>
            <p>Afterwards, ſeveral Nations pretended to be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of this moſt uſeful Art, (and perhaps it might be found out by ſeveral people, who had yet no commerce one with another, neceſſity being ingenious under all Climates.) But the <hi>Phoenicians</hi> put in the faireſt, who as they are accounted the Authors of Arithmetick and Aſtronomy, ſo alſo of Navigation, whence is that of <hi>Tibullus:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Prima ratem ventis credere docta Tyrus.</q>
            <p>They were the firſt that took the obſervation of the North Star, in ſuppliment to the Naval myſtery. But <hi>Herodotus</hi> complains, that theſe <hi>Phoenicians,</hi> who came with <hi>Cadmus</hi> into <hi>Greece,</hi> as they civilized the people, by their Sciences and Literature, ſo they exceedingly debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched them by their Luxury and inſatiable avarice, which together with their Merchandiſe they firſt imported thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The <hi>Greeks</hi> call them <hi>Phoenicians,</hi> but the <hi>Hebrews Canaanites.</hi> Their Country is the Sea-coaſt of <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Tyrus,</hi> the maritime Metropolis thereof bordering upon the Tribe of <hi>Zabulun,</hi> whoſe Trade and Commerce was ſo great and remarkable in the days of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> that two whole Chapters are ſpent in the deſcription of her vaſtneſs, and judgments. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 26 &amp; 27. She is there
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29662:10"/> ſtil'd a Merchant, whoſe Ships were made of Firr, their Maſts of Cedar, their Oars of <hi>Baſhan</hi> Oak, the Hatches of Ivory, the Waſte-cloths, Vanes, Flaggs and Pendants of Purple and Scarlet. The common Mariners were the <hi>Zidonians,</hi> and Inhabitants of <hi>Arvad,</hi> their Calkers were the Antients of <hi>Gebal,</hi> and their Pilots the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Tyrus.</hi> Near unto ſuch ingenious and thriving Neighbours was the lot of <hi>Zabulun.</hi> But they had alſo Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens of their own, upon the Sea of <hi>Galilee, Capharnaum, Bethſaida</hi> and <hi>Tiberias,</hi> where probably they took in the Oyl, the Wine and Corn of their Brother <hi>Iſſachar.</hi> So ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageouſly were they ſituated, both for the advantages of the moſt ingenious and uſeful converſation, as alſo for the advancement of their Trade and Commerce. And it is very like, they much improved themſelves hereby: For in the Song of <hi>Deborah,</hi> we read of thoſe of <hi>Zabulun</hi> to handle the Pen of the Writer, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5. 14. And it might not be improper they ſhould handle the Pen of the Law, who were to be the Trumpeters of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>And Iſſachar,</hi> &amp;c. The Text gives a character of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> like that which the Poets uſually give of the firſt and beſt men of the World, that is, that he finding a rich Soil, was content to labour for his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, to pay his Gabel, to enjoy, through the ſweat of his Brows, the Treaſures of the Sands, and the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Earth, containing himſelf within his own bounds, without encroaching upon the Lands or Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens of <hi>Zabulun,</hi> which ſeem ſtrangely to break the ſquare of his Portion and Inheritance. And though the Heraldry of the ninth Son of <hi>Jacob,</hi> promiſe no great effects either in Arts or Arms, yet in the Wars of <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David, 1 Chron.</hi> 12. 32. the children of <hi>Iſſachar</hi> were aſſembled for <hi>David,</hi> under the command of two hundred Captains of their own Tribe, <hi>who were
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29662:10"/> men that had underſtanding of the times, to know what Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael ought to do.</hi> To teach us that the wiſeſt men do not always deſcend from Kings, from Prieſts, or from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls; but ſometimes creep from under the humble ſhades of poor Tents and innocent Cottages, to confound the pride of the Great and diſſolute, to ſit in counſel with Princes, and to determine the great affairs of War and Peace, or to adminiſter relief and juſtice, deliverance and comfort to the oppreſſed world.</p>
            <p>We might add hereunto, that the Countries of <hi>Zabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lun</hi> and <hi>Iſſachar</hi> have been the Cradles of many great and deſerving Princes, as well as the ſcenes of glorious actions. But, to omit all other how conſiderable ſoever, let us caſt our eyes upon our Saviour, who honour'd <hi>Nazareth</hi> with his conception, Mount <hi>Tabor</hi> with his Transfiguration, <hi>Capharnaum</hi> and the Sea-Coaſts of <hi>Galilee</hi> with his Doctrine, his Miracles, his Converſation; and vouchſafed from thence alſo to chuſe his Diſciples, to call the people out of the valley of the ſhadow of Death, unto the Mountain of light and life, to offer the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices not of Bulls or of Goats, but thoſe of an humble and contrite ſpirit, which through the merits of that one unſpotted Sacrifice, which was once offer'd up for us all upon the Croſs, become Sacrifices of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, holy and acceptable unto the Lord. <hi>Wherefore rejoice, Zabulun,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>They ſhall call the people, &amp;c.</hi> From this prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Benediction of the good Patriarch we may obſerve,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the ſureſt foundation to lay the hopes of a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture proſperity, is true piety. The doctrines of all good men, the examples of all Ages, both of the good and bad, and even the dictates of reaſon it ſelf aſtipulate for this doctrine. If we look back as far as the Laws of <hi>Moſes,</hi> we find that great Conductor of Gods people
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29662:11"/> ever preſſing this doctrine, as the only means to obtain their promis'd Land, and poſſeſs it, when attain'd. <hi>Deut. 6. 18. Thou ſhalt do that which is right and good in the ſight of the Lord, that it may be well with thee, and that thou maieſt go in and poſſeſs the good Land, which the Lord ſware unto thy Fathers.</hi> It is this Song, which ſo often exerciſes the harp of <hi>David.</hi> Pſal. 34. 9. <hi>O fear the Lord, O ye his Saints: For there is no want to them that fear him.</hi> And after all his experience and obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he aſſures us, <hi>Pſal. 37. 25. I have been young, and now am old, yet never ſaw I the righteous forſaken, nor his ſeed begging their bread.</hi> The wiſeſt of men tells us, <hi>Prov. 10. 27. The fear of the Lord prolongeth life.</hi> And it is very obſervable what <hi>Epiphanius</hi> remarks con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the former ages of the world, namely, that there was not one example of a Son, who died before his Father, till <hi>Terah,</hi> the Father of <hi>Abraham,</hi> taught the people a falſe Religion to make Images of Clay and worſhip them, and concerning him it was firſt ſaid, <hi>Gen. 11. 28. And Haran died before his father Terah, in the Land of his Nativity.</hi> Pointing out to us that it was the Impiety of men, which brought all the evils in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, and haſten'd the ſlow neceſſities of Death. But to what purpoſe ſhall we multiply examples? St. <hi>Paul</hi> plainly tells us, 1 <hi>Tim. 4. 8. Godlineſs is profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table unto all things, having the promiſe of this life, and that which is to come.</hi> This doctrine he had receiv'd from the fountain of truth, as it is now recorded, <hi>Mat. 6. 33. But ſeek ye firſt the Kingdom of God, and his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you.</hi> In ſhort, then it was piety that carried <hi>Joſeph</hi> to all the honours of <hi>Egypt,</hi> that gave victory to <hi>David,</hi> and riches to <hi>Sol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n;</hi> that brought the wicked Head of <hi>Holofernes</hi> into the lap of <hi>Judith,</hi> and threw <hi>Eſther</hi> into the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29662:11"/> of the mightieſt Prince then upon earth. But it is not neceſſary to ſtand upon the ſucceſs, that has always attended particular devotion: It were beyond our Arithmetick to number them. All thoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, which have been founded in piety and religious Laws, have ever flouriſht with a laſting proſperity. Upon this baſis, was laid the Jewiſh Synagogue, which endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the amazement of the World for ſo many Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; and if there were any ſad Contingences, that befell it, it is nothing but the due reward of their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and revolting from God. And the Chriſtian Church was built upon the Mountain of piety, to be the glory of all Ages, the honour of Kings, the deſire of all the World, To ſuck of the abundance of the Seas, &amp;<hi>c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there are two vices oppoſite to a well grounded and ſolid piety, and conſequently to a firm and well eſtabliſht proſperity, and thoſe are a too rapacious Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, and an over-haſty Ambition.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Avarice. <hi>Job</hi> tells us there are thoſe, that build their houſes as a Moth, <hi>Job</hi> 27. 18. And how does it build? Eaſie obſervation ſhews, that this little creature harbour'd in ſome piece of Cloth, gnaws perpetually to cover himſelf, till his greedineſs has devoured the walls of his houſe, and ſo he diſcovers his own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs inſtead of hiding himſelf. Thus does every Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous man: He wracks himſelf and torments others, to raiſe a Monument of his greatneſs or ſecurity: But this goodly building compos'd of Injuſtice, Rapines and Oppreſſions, cemented together with the Sweat and Blood of the poor, crumbles into ruin; and when this cometh into the judgement of God, this fooliſh Moth, who has ſo gnawn, to feed and cover himſelfe; finds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf naked, hungry and extreamly miſerable. So true
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29662:12"/> is that of the Prophet <hi>Hab. 2. 9, 10, 11. Wo to him that covets an evil covetouſneſs to his houſe, that he may ſet his Neſt on high, that he may be delivered from the power of evil. Thou haſt conſulted ſhame to thine houſe, by cutting off many people, and haſt ſinned againſt thy Soul. For the ſtone ſhall cry out of the Wall, and the Beam out of the Timber ſhall anſwer it.</hi> So that inſtead of ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Treaſures of the Sand, their portion is only thoſe of the Snow, which God ſpeaks to <hi>Job</hi> of, (<hi>Job 38. 22. Haſt thou entred into the treaſures of the Snow?</hi>) And of which one of the Fathers makes a very uſeful Moral, telling us, that the Treaſures of the Snow are Wordly Riches, which covetous men rake together, as children do Snow, which in their folly they roll into heaps, with no little pains and hazards of their health, efforming them into Horſes, Giants, Houſes, fanſying ſtrength, uſefulneſs and ſafety in theſe more feeble works of their feeble hands; but the next ſhowre wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhes away all their labours, leaving nothing behind, but the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe white fleeces, which foams a while upon the pavement, and preſently ſinks into the boſom of the earth. So ſlippery are all the acquiſts of cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, that they ſcarce ever ſtay ſo long with us as to be enjoy'd, never ſo long as we expected, nor at all to ſatisfie us. <hi>But as for the man that feareth the Lord, that delighteth greatly in his commandment, bleſſed is he. His ſeed ſhall be mighty upon earth; the generation of the upright ſhall be bleſſed. Wealth and Riches ſhall be in his Houſe, and his Righteouſneſs endureth for ever.</hi> Pſalm 112. 1, 2, 3.</p>
            <p n="2">2. An overhaſty ambition. Have you ever ſeen a bubble riſe in a moment, and take a dance or two in the lap of the Wave, his Mother, and then burſt aſunder, and immediately ſhrink again into his firſt principles?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29662:12"/> Then have you ſeen the emblem of an ambitious man, who riſing from almoſt as great a weakneſs, ſwells bigg, and fetches a caper, or two, and perhaps breaks two or three more bubbles, that float in his way, and by and by ſome heavier drop of adverſity falls upon his head, and cruſhes him into his firſt Original. This is exemplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us in the adventures of the Conſul <hi>Bibulus,</hi> who ſwelling in his triumphant Chariot, was kill'd by the accidental fall of a Tileſtone before he could reach the Capitol. Or in the great Favourite <hi>Sejanus,</hi> whom the ſame day ſaw attended by the Senate, and torn to pieces by the people. Or in the Sacred Hiſtory, where we find <hi>Abſalom</hi> impatient of the long and (as ſeem'd to him) more than humane age of his Father, and thereupon ſets all his engins at work to bring the Crown upon his own head: But the event was only, that having by a reſtleſs ambition diſturbed the Court of his aged Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, every hair of that buſie head became a ſnare to him, and an Executioner of the Divine Juſtice. So infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly does ruin follow Pride and Rebellion.</p>
            <p>Put all into this L'envoy, and it amounts to this, That fortunes raiſed upon unjuſt ambitions, or covetous exactions, are as houſes built upon ſands, which waſh away with every ſtorm, ſcarce leaving behind them the name of their ruins, while exemplar pieties found their proſperities upon Rocks, which no winds, nor rains can move from their place. And the reaſon of it is, Becauſe Religion puts us under the protection of God, without whoſe bleſſing nothing is ſafe, nothing is ſucceſsful. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it becomes all thoſe, who imbark themſelves in the dangers, and employments of the world, to ſecure the bleſſings of Heaven, and the favours of God by zealous devotions, and conſtant piety. For then the Stars ſhall fight in their courſes, the winds ſhall blow, the Sea
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29662:13"/> ſhall ſpread her ſelf as a carpet, the earth ſhall open all the Magazines and Riches of her Entrails: <hi>And they ſhall ſuck the abundance of the Seas, and Treaſures,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Why is it then that we ſee ſo many fruitleſs, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fatal Voyages? Why does the Sea ſo often raiſe her Waves, as the Mountains of <hi>Ararat,</hi> and then open her unfathomable Womb, as if ſhe meant to diſcloſe the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails and Centre of nature? Why does the Air ſo often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the emblem of Hell, rending all things with the fury of its lightnings, and by and by hide the ruins made, in darkneſs, thick, as that of the infernal Abyſs? How comes it to paſs, that Fleets fraught with the Riches of the Eaſt and of the Weſt, ſo often ſplit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Rocks and wreck upon ſands? How comes ſo great wealth to be a prey to the Ocean, and ſo many bodies of men to be food for Sherks and Dolphins? Why is Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo deaf in the midſt of theſe tempeſts, that neither Tears, nor Vows, nor Prayers can move it to mercy? Why; it is becauſe men carry along with them into the Deep their Intemperances, Adulteries, Blaſphemies, Oaths, Curſes, Rapines, and the whole Mafs of their Sins unrepented of. This is that accurſed Cargo, that Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, that makes the Seas to ſwell, and the Winds to roar, that ſtops the ears of Heaven to their call, and makes an eternal ſhipwreck of their ſouls, bodies and eſtates. So intolerable a weight does ſin add to the calamities of men, and ſo backward is God in redreſſing the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the wicked. This brings to my remembrance a ſtory, which <hi>Diogenes Laertius</hi> reports of <hi>Prias</hi> of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ene,</hi> who being at Sea in a ſtorm with ſome wicked Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, and they calling upon their Gods for relief, the wiſe Philoſopher adviſed them to ſilence (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) leſt the Gods ſhould be aware of their paſſage. The vengeance, not the mercy of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29662:13"/> Divinity always purſuing the ungodly. Which ſhould teach us above all things to learn the Golden Verſe of <hi>Orpheus,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;<hi>c.</hi>) to make Religion the firſt, and laſt, and all our cares, that we may be preſerved from all dangers, or ſecur'd in them by the Divine Protection; or rather that of a more Divine Poet, <hi>Pſal. 91. 2, 3, 4. I will ſay of the Lord, he is my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge and my fortreſs; my God in him will I truſt. Surely he ſhall deliver thee from the ſnare of the Fowler, and from the noiſome peſtilence. He ſhall cover thee with his Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and under his Wings ſhalt thou truſt, his truth ſhall be thy Shield and Buckler. Thou ſhalt not be afraid for the terrour by night, nor for the Arrow that flies by day; nor for the peſtilence that walks in darkneſs, nor for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction that waſtes at noon day. A thouſand ſhall fall at thy ſide, and ten thouſand at thy right hand, but it ſhall not come nigh thee. For he ſhall give his Angels charge over thee to keep thee in all thy ways,</hi> v. 11. His favour is the beſt policy and firmeſt Inſurance.</p>
            <p>But there are thoſe (and particularly S. <hi>Ambroſe de bendict. Patriarch.</hi>) who have more advantageouſly, and more worthy a Prophetick Spirit, diſcourſt this ſubject, referring the Doctrine to Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and telling us that out of <hi>Zabulun</hi> Chriſt ſent them to call the people to the Mountain, &amp;<hi>c. (i. e.)</hi> to the Church, who ſuckt the abundance of the Seas, and Treaſures hid in the Sand, when the bounty of Kings, convert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Faith, enricht the Church with the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of their Donations: Which happy and pious Interpretation gives us occaſion to handle Doctrines the moſt uſeful, and myſteries the moſt profound. And</p>
            <p n="1">1. We obſerve what improbable Inſtruments, in the eyes of men, God choſe to call his people to the Mountain: He fetches no Diſciples out of the Schools
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29662:14"/> of the <hi>Phariſees;</hi> he ſends not to the Walls or Porches of <hi>Athens,</hi> but calls a few Fiſherman to give Laws and Religion to all the Nations, and all the Ages of the World: Of which <hi>Origen cont. Celſ. l.</hi> 1. gives the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, telling us that if Chriſt had choſen the wiſe and eloquent, it might have given ſuſpicion, that like the Gentile Philoſophers, he had raiſed his Sect, not by the Grace of God, but by the Arts and Elocution of his followers. But when we ſee a few Publicans and Fiſhers convince the obſtinacy of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and baffle the learning of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> what can we ſay elſe, but that the Prophecy of <hi>Jeremy</hi> is fulfilled? <hi>Jer. 16. 16. I will ſend for many Fiſhers, and they ſhall fiſh them;</hi> and the call of Chriſt become effectual to the Salvation of the World, <hi>Mat. 4. 19. Follow me, and I will make ye Fiſhers of men.</hi> All which S. <hi>Paul</hi> very well expreſſes 1 <hi>Cor. 2. 4, 5. My ſpeech was not in the enticing words of mans wiſdom, but in demonſtration of the Spirit and of power: That your faith ſhould not ſtand in the wiſdom of men, but in the power of God.</hi> Go then, buſy Stateſman, lay the uncemented bulk of thy future deſigns upon the tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Baſis of thy own Wiſdom: Deviſe Laws, joyn Intereſts, oppreſs thine Enemies, plot againſt whom thou ſuſpecteſt, cajoul thy Friends, and remove all the poſſible obſtacles of thy greatneſs: All this while thou doſt no more, than what the trifling fancies of men uſually practiſe upon a Cloud, making Dragons, Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maera's, and Armed men, fighting according to their own conceits, and preſently the Wind drives them away, and all that they beheld with admiration in the Heavens, falls down in Water upon their Heads, and makes Mortar under their feet. All our wiſdom is folly, all our ſtrength is weakneſs; it is God only that can manifeſt his power in our infirmities, and turn all
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29662:14"/> our imperfections to his Glory. It was he alone, that upon the weak foundation of theſe poor Sons of <hi>Zabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lun</hi> (weak indeed in the eyes of men, but what can be weak that is ſupported by the Arm of God?) built his Church to continue the admiration and glory of all the world till time ſhall be no more. It was he alone that could ſtrengthen the moſt abject perſons in the World to go through all the oppoſitions of humane wit, or ſtrength, or malice, to drive the Oracles from their Stools, and the falſe Gods from their Temples, placing in their rooms the Doctrine and Croſs of Jeſus. It was he that by the preaching of theſe ſilly Orators united together people of Nations ſo diſtant, of natures ſo unlike, of manners ſo different, and in Religion ſo diſagreeing, to ſerve him for ever in the Communion of the Catholick Church, giving <hi>ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and ſome Evangeliſts, and ſome Paſtors and Teachers; for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the body of Chriſt: Till we all come in the unity of Faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt.</hi> Eph. 4. 11, 12, 13. <hi>Why then do the Heathen rage, and why do the people imagine a vain thing? The Kings of the Earth ſtood up, and the Rulers took counſel to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt the Lord, and againſt his anointed. Yet for all this have I ſet my King upon my Holy Hill of Sion.</hi> Pſ. 2. O unfathomable abyſs of the Divine Wiſdom and Power! that <hi>out of the mouths of Babes and Sucklings haſt ordained ſtrength, that thou mighteſt ſtill the Enemy and Avenger;</hi> that by ſuch contemptible means haſt daſht to pieces the ſtrength and polity of the World, like a Potters Veſſel, to advance the trophies of thy on, and to ſhew us that nothing is too weak to accompliſh the ends of God.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:29662:15"/>
            <p>But if we ſhall ſearch into the Hiſtory of this ſort of men, we ſhall find them to have had the firſt hand in the greateſt tranſactions of the World, as if God had on purpoſe choſe always to make uſe of Fiſher-men to give the firſt motion to thoſe Wheels, that ſhould ſet all the reſt agoing. For if, as S. <hi>Baſil</hi> obſerves, (<hi>Baſ. Hexam.) Adam</hi> firſt exercis'd his faculties, where God gave him his firſt Dominion, he was firſt a <hi>Peter</hi> man, and the Sea the earlieſt Scene of Humane action. And yet the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Traditions run far beyond this, telling us that God in the fifth day of the Creation form'd the <hi>Behemoth</hi> and <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and finding them too big for one Element, pickled up the one to be the food of the Elect in the time of the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi> And though this ſtory grounded upon that paſſage 2 <hi>Eſar.</hi> 6. 49. may ſeem to ſome a fable more ridiculous than the Whale of <hi>Lucian;</hi> yet if this mighty Whale, which no Element can contain, be but the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and Fiſh of the Sibyls, then is this Parable ſuch as contains the greateſt myſtery of the Chriſtian Faith, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and tells us in plain <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God, and the Saviour of the World, that he is the Bread of Life, and the food of the Elect. Which may illuſtrate, or at leaſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large our contemplations upon thoſe words of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>Mat. 7. 10. If he ask a Fiſh, will he give him a Serpent?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> was drawn out of the Waters, as his name imports, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2. 10. to lay the foundation of the Synagogne, which like his Ark built of Bulruſhes, Bitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Pitch, moral, ceremonial and politick Laws, floated its Votaries upon the uncertain Waves of a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome World, till the Kings Daughter ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them into the favours and honours of her King.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29662:15"/> 
               <hi>Ita nos piſciculi ſecundum <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> noſtrum Jeſum Chriſtam in aquâ naſcimur, nec aliter, quàm in aquâ permanendo, ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi ſumus. Tert. de Bapt. c.</hi> 1. Let Infidels and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, like Aſps and Vipers, draw poiſon from the dry and barren Sand, Water is the Element of Fiſh, and Regenerate of God.</p>
            <p>The Gentiles too owe much of their Religion, and much of their knowledge to the <hi>Hebber-men</hi> of <hi>Coos,</hi> who at one lucky draught brought up the famous <hi>Tripos,</hi> whoſe ternary of Feet denote the full perfection of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the great prerogative of <hi>Apollo:</hi> So that while <hi>Janus</hi> keeps the Storks off from behind, and blindly peeps forward to future events, the God of <hi>Delphos</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in the knowledge of all Tenſes, paſt, preſent, and to come. And truly this Oracle did ſo ſtrangely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant the ſpirits of men, given over to ſuperſtition, falſe fears, and unreaſonable hopes, that he grew famous through the Univerſe: Kings and Councellors, the greateſt and the wiſeſt men upon Earth, ſent to him in all doubtful affairs, (to perplex them the more) as willing to be cheated with the ambiguity of his Anſwers. In this reputation he flouriſht for many Ages, till the <hi>Hebrew</hi> Boy packt him from his Altars, and ſunk him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a darkneſs, like that of his Reſponſes.</p>
            <p>Then it was that God ſent the true Fiſher-men, the Apoſtles, with the true <hi>Tripos</hi> and myſtery of the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Wiſdom of the Father, the expectation of the paſt, the glory of the preſent, the hopes of the future, and Salvation of all the ages of the World. Fraught with this Wiſdom, theſe poor Ideots fail'd through the World, ſtopt the mouths of the Philoſophers, ſilenced the Oracles, deſtroyed the falſe Gods, baniſht Satan out of his Kingdom, converted the Nations; and maugre all the malice of Hell and wicked men, planted the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29662:16"/> of Jeſus Chriſt over the moſt famous Kingdomes of the Univerſe: And as S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> obſerves, it was no obſtacle to their proceedings, that they were few or unlearned, or private perſons, or that they preacht auſtere and unwonted Doctrines, or that mankind was prepoſſeſt with old Laws and old Cuſtomes. But the previous grace of God took away all theſe hindrances, turning their infirmities into ſtrength, their ignorance into wiſdom, their ſtripes into joy, their impriſonments into liberty, and all their impediments to the advantages of Religion. Inſomuch that they daily converted mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes in every Nation from falſe principles and diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute lives; from the ſlavery of Sin and Satan, to ſerve the living God in ſoberneſs, righteouſneſs and godlineſs. So plentiful was the draught of Fiſh, when God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Net to be let down.</p>
            <p>And now what more uſeful Application can we make of all this, than that which <hi>Syracides</hi> obſerves, <hi>Ecclus. 3. 19. Many are in high place, and of renown; but myſteries are reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the meek.</hi> Their minds are the freeſt from the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations of paſſions and unruly affections, and therefore the fitteſt receptacles of the Divine Truth. And as S. <hi>Baſil</hi> in <hi>Praef. in Iſa.</hi> diſcourſing concerning the diverſities of gifts, tells us, that a mind ſtain'd with ſin, like an abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Looking-glaſs, renders but a broken and confuſed Image: And as we cannot ſee our faces in any matter but in ſuch only as is ſmooth and pellucid; ſo there is required a meekneſs and clearneſs of Soul for the right perception and reflection of Heavenly verities. Hence it is that we ſee ſo many of the learned World Artheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal in their principles, ſo many great men diſſolute in their lives, and ſo many people every where ignorant or careleſs of their Salvation. Not that they are incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to apprehend the Doctrines, or unable to practiſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29662:16"/> the duties, but becauſe they have ſullied the purities and clearneſs of their Souls with the luſts and evil habits of their Bodies, and ſo render'd them unfit for Holy Myſteries. A man might meaſure the motions and diſtances of the Stars, might act in the moſt important affairs of the World, muſter Armies, fit Navies, pitch Battels, though he came from his laſt nights ſurfeit, and his eyes were yet red with Wine; but a man can never ſay his Prayers, or ſerve his God till his paſſions are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calm'd, and his mind brought to a certain frame and evenneſs. Nay, it will be hard to receive, or long to retain any true Idea of God or his Religion, ſo long as our Luſts, his Enemies, are our Maſters, as is viſible in the Gentiles, who <hi>when they knew God, glorified him not as God, neither were thankful, but became vain in their imaginations, and their fooliſh heart was darken'd, Rom.</hi> 1. 21. Till by the meekneſs of the Goſpel, this Prodigal was brought to himſelf. And I am apt to think that ſome meek and humble Cottagers have better notions concerning God and his word, than any proud inflate Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher. And this might be the reaſon of our Saviours great rejoycing in Spirit, <hi>Luk. 10. 21. I thank thee, O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Lord of Heaven and Earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and prudent, and revealed them unto Babes: Even ſo, Father, for ſo it ſeemed good in they ſight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>They ſhall offer the Sacrifices of Righteouſneſs:</hi> S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> recounts ten Sacrifices, not enjoined by Law, but ſuch as become the Evangelical Grace. The firſt is that Spiritual and Myſtical gift, mentioned by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Eph. 5. 1. <hi>Be ye followers of God, as dear Children, and walk in love as Chriſt alſo hath loved us, and given himſelf for us, an offering, and a Sacrifice to God for a ſweet ſmelling ſavour.</hi> The ſecond is the blood of the Martyrs, or the virtues and holy life of the mortified.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29662:17"/> Rom. 12. 1. <hi>I beſeech you therefore, Brethren, by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, that ye preſent your Bodies a living Sacrifice, boly and acceptable to God, which is your reaſonable ſervice.</hi> The third that of Prayer, Pſal. 141. 2. <hi>Let my Prayer be ſet forth before thee, as Incenſe, and the lifting up of my hands, as the evening Sacrifice.</hi> The fourth is the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant warbles of Hymns, and the grateful returns of Praiſes to the Divine Majeſty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116. 17. The fifth is Juſtice, which the noble Prophet calls upon the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for with ſo much Zeal, <hi>Iſa. 1. 17. Ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well, ſeek judgement.</hi> The ſixth, Alms and mercy, according to S. <hi>James c. 1. 27. Pure Religion and undefiled before God and the Father is this, to viſit the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans and Widows in their affliction.</hi> The ſeventh is the Jubile and exulation in the Victories and Glories of Chriſt, as the Prophet ſpeaks Iſa. 26. 1, 2. <hi>In that day ſhall this Song be ſung in the Land of Judah, We have a ſtrong City: Salvation will God appoint for walls and bulwarks. Open the Gates, that the righteous Nation, which keepeth the truth, may enter in.</hi> Then it is that <hi>Zabulun ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice:</hi> Then <hi>ſhall he ſuck of the abundance of the Seas, and treaſures hid in the Sand. Then ſhall the Daughter of Tyre be there with a gift, even the rich among the people. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of thy Fathers thou ſhalt have Children, whom thou mayeſt make Princes in all Lands. And we will remember the name of the Lord from generation to generation, and all the people ſhall give him thanks world without end,</hi> Pſ. 45. The eight is the Sacrifice of an humble and contrite Spirit, which however deſpicable in the eyes of men is more acceptable to God than a thouſand <hi>Holocauſts.</hi> The ninth is the preaching of the Goſpel, whereof S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo often glories, and particularly <hi>Rom</hi> 15 16. exults in the Grace of God, by which he was called to <hi>be a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Jeſus Chriſt to the Gentiles, miniſtring the Goſpel of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29662:17"/> God, that the ſacrificing up of the Gentiles might be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, being ſanctified by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Happy S. <hi>Paul,</hi> who with thy fiery Tongue didſt burn ſo many reaſonable Sacrifices to God! Happy S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> too in this Sacrifice, who firſt offering to God the Calves of thy Golden Lips, didſt afterward preſent ſo many wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Holocauſts</hi> of Converts unto the Eternal Majeſty! Happy the Gentiles in a Doctor to preach the myſteries of the Eternal Word, to convert Nations, to convince Hereticks, to reduce wanderers, and bring all men into the paths of Salvation! And thou once happy City of <hi>Conſtantine!</hi> while thou didſt cheriſh the moſt eloquent of men, who ſanctified all the Learning of the <hi>Grecians</hi> by the Holineſs of his mouth, and offer'd to God ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the moſt acceptable Sacrifices, the Spirits of Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes, won by the irreſiſtible charms of his Oratory, and mortified to the ſeverities of Repentance, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Croſs. <hi>Glory be given to God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who gaveſt ſuch gifts unto men.</hi> May there riſe in every generation ſuch perſons as may imitate their Sanctity, Zeal and Induſtry, and being bleſſed by thy goodneſs, may bring many Souls to thee, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain True Doctrine and Holy Diſcipline in thy Church, till the ſecond coming of Chriſt our Saviour. The tenth is Charitable beneficence to the houſhold of Faith, as witneſſeth S. <hi>Paul,</hi> Phil. 4. 18. <hi>I received the things that were ſent, an odour of a ſweet ſmell, a Sacrifice accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the firſt is that alone which can make the reſt acceptable before God, and without which the Prayers of the moſt devout, the blood of the Martyrs, the alms of the moſt Charitable, and the Religion of all mankind were ineffectual to their Salvation. It is by this Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice alone our ſins are waſh'd, our natures purified, our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29662:18"/> duties rewarded, and the Chriſtian Faith ſecured of the glories of Eternity. O bleſſed Jeſus! O Eternal Son of God! Who can ſufficiently admire this myſtery, or adore thy goodneſs? Who can ſufficiently extol thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible love, who gaveſt not thy Wealth, not thy Brethren, not thy Kindred, not thy Angels, but thy ſelf, God and Man, for us Sinners and Enemies? Pious Devotions have been carried into many admirable rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the contemplation of this ſublime Myſtery; but none ſeems to have gone higher than that of <hi>Origen,</hi> who urges this great High Prieſt to have offer'd himſelf not for man only, but to have taſted death <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the merits and efficacy of his paſſion to the Stars, otherwiſe impure in the ſight of God, and therefore in need to be cleanſed; that ſo all things might be reſtored to the Kingdom of the Father. <hi>Orig. in Evang. Joh.</hi> And which S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems highly to favour in that famous place of <hi>Col. 1. 19, 20. For it pleaſed the Father, that in him ſhould all fulneſs dwell, and (having made peace through the Blood of his Croſs) by him to reconcile all things unto himſelf; by him, I ſay, whether they be things in Earth or things in Heaven.</hi> If this be ſo, we need not break the Glaſſes of <hi>Galiloeo;</hi> the ſpots may be waſhed out of the Sun, and total nature ſanctified unto God that made it. However this may be, it is ſafeſt for us to attend to Holy Scriptures telling us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. that <hi>the Son of God offer'd, through the Eternal Spirit, this Sacrifice upon the Croſs, to purge our Conſciences from dead works to ſerve the living God: And he is not now enter'd into the holy places made with hands, but into heaven it ſelf now to appear in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God for us.</hi> Which is to ſay in effect that Chriſt offered himſelf a Sacrifice upon the Croſs, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was perfect, and infinitely meritorious, could be but one, and that but once; but becauſe the needs of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29662:18"/> the World ſhould laſt as long as the World it ſelf, it was neceſſary there ſhould be a perpetual Miniſtry eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht, whereby this one ſufficient Sacrifice ſhould be made for ever effectual to the ſeveral new ariſing needs of all the World. To this end Chriſt was made a Prieſt for ever, not that he ſhould offer himſelf often: <hi>For then muſt he often have ſuffer'd ſince the foundation of the World, Heb.</hi> 9 25. But being aſcended into Heaven, he there repreſents and exhibits to the Father the great effective Sacrifice (which he offer'd on the Croſs) to eternal and never failing purpoſes.</p>
            <p>And as Chriſt is pleas'd to repreſent to his Father that great Sacrifice as a means of atonement and expiation for all mankind, and with ſpecial purpoſes for all the elect, all that ſerve him in holineſs: So he has appointed that the ſame miniſtry ſhall be done on Earth too, in our manner, and according to our promotion. And therefore he choſe firſt the Fiſher-men of <hi>Galilee</hi> to offer the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Righteouſneſs, and has ever ſince preſerved in his Church an order of men, who by ſhewing forth the Lords death by Sacramental repreſentation, may pray unto God after the ſame manner that our Lord and High Prieſt does, that is, offer to God, and repreſent in this moſt ſolemn Prayer and Sacrament, Chriſt as once for all, offer'd already upon the Altar of the Croſs: So ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up a gracious inſtrument, whereby our Prayers may for his ſake, and in the ſame manner of Interceſſion be offer'd up to God in our behalf, and for all them for whom we pray, to all thoſe purpoſes for which Chriſt died.</p>
            <p>And as the Holy Prieſts do in a Sacramental manner preſent to God the Sacrifice of the Croſs by being Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators of Chriſts Interceſſion: So the people are Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers too in their manner: For that beſides in ſaying <hi>Amen,</hi> they join in the Act of him that miniſters, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29662:19"/> make it alſo to be their own: So when they worthily receive the Holy Euchariſt, they receive Chriſt within them, and therefore may alſo offer him to God, while in their Sacrifice of Obedience and Thankſgiving, they preſent themſelves to God with Chriſt, whom they have Spiritually received, that is, themſelves with that, which will make them gracious and acceptable. The offering their Bodies and Souls and ſervices to God in him, and by him and with him, who is his Fathers well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloved, and in whom he is well pleaſed, cannot but be acceptable to all the purpoſes of bleſſing, grace and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. And this is the Sacrifice of Righteouſneſs, the <hi>Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha purum,</hi> ſpoken of by the Prophet <hi>Malachi 1. 11. From the riſing of the Sun, even unto the going down of the ſame, my name ſhall be great among the Gentiles, and in every place Incenſe ſhall be offer'd unto my name, and a pure offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; For my name ſhall be great among the Heathen, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> Wherefore let us all exult in that myſtical expreſſion of the Son of <hi>Barachiah,</hi> Zech. 9. 17. <hi>How great is his goodneſs, and how great is his beauty? Corn ſhall make the young men cheerful, and new Wine the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>They ſhall ſuck of the abundance of the Seas, and of Treaſures,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thoſe (as hath been noted before) how ſtudy myſtical ſenſes of Holy Scripture, refer all this to the Doctrine of Chriſt and the calling of his Apoſtles: For in theſe parts he was not only much converſant himſelf, but alſo choſe many of his Diſciples and Followers, who though in their own perſons they did not <hi>ſuck of the abundance of the Seas, or treaſures of the Sand, (i. e.</hi>) the Riches and Emoluments of the two Elements; yet they did in the Body which they built, and in the perſons of their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, the Biſhops and Paſtors of the Church. For
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29662:19"/> when Emperours and Kings became Proſelytes of the Goſpel, they became kind to the Church, and ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came rich by their Donations. The wealth of all Seas flowed into the boſome of the Church, and the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of all Lands was laid at the feet of the ſervants of Jeſus. Then was fulfilled that of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa. 60. 4, 5. Lift up thine eyes round about, and ſee; all they gather themſelves together, they come to thee: thy Sons ſhall come from far, and thy daughters ſhall be nurſed at thy ſide. Then thou ſhalt ſee, and flow together, and thine heart ſhall fear and be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged; becauſe the abundance of the Sea ſhall be converted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, the forces of the Gentiles ſhall come unto thee.</hi> As if he had ſaid, Look about thee, little flock; fear not: All this ſtrength, theſe Arms, this wealth of Sea and Land, all this Wit, Learning, Arts and Sciences, and whatever thou beholdeſt now, ſo obſtinately ſet againſt thee, ſhall all come in and proſtrate themſelves at thy feet, for thy defence, ſupport and ornament: For as the ſame Prophet, <hi>chap. 49. 22, 23. Behold I will lift up mine hand to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and ſet up my Standard to the people, ſaith the Lord, and they ſhall bring my Sons in their Arms, and thy Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhall be carried upon their ſhoulders. And Kings ſhall be thy nurſing-fathers, and Queens thy nurſing-mothers: They ſhall bow down to thee with their face toward the Earth, and lick up the duſt of thy feet, and thou ſhalt know that I am the Lord: For they ſhall not be aſhamed that wait for me.</hi> Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Monarchs, to be made the Parents of a Religion ſo holy and ſo ſalutiferous to men! May the Eternal Jeſus, the Prince of Peace, bleſs your Perſons, unite your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, ſtrengthen your Arms, that Religion may daily ſpread it ſelf under your conduct, over all the corners of the World: May the Enemies of God (if any) ſeel the force of your Weapons, and ſee the Trophies of your Valours; but being at unity amongſt your ſelves, may we (who profeſs
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:29662:20"/> the name of Jeſus) ever ſerve him in the beauty of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, in the decency of Order, in the protections of Peace, and if poſſible, in the bleſſings of Unity. But above all, mayſt thou ever be happy, Great Defender of the Faith Apoſtolick, ever triumphant over the Enemies of thy Peace and ours: May thy reign never ceaſe, O Breath of our noſtrils, but having long protected us in Peace, and the enjoyments of a moſt happy Religion, mayſt thou be tranſlated to the Kingdom of Jeſus, to raign with him for ever. And may all the outward ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages of Religion ſerve only for her defence and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ornament, for the ſuppreſſion of Hereſie, Schiſm, and all ungodlineſs and licentious diſorder: but never mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to our Covetouſneſs, Pride, Luſt, or other enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; that ſo we may ever worſhip the Divine Majeſty in the profeſſion and practice of that truth and holineſs, which becomes the redeemed of the Lord Jeſus. And in order hereunto, the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, by his Eternal Spirit make us all faithful in our Miniſtry, devout in our Prayers, powerful in our Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, pure in the adminiſtration of his Holy Sacraments, charitable in good works, temperate in our lives, meek and humble in our converſations, and bring a plentiful Harveſt to his Kingdom by our labours.</p>
            <p>There is alſo another ſenſe of theſe words, which, though far more remote, is yet of greateſt advantage to <hi>Zabulun</hi> and <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> and indeed unto us all; and that is, Chriſt himſelf ſhall the moſt happily accompliſh this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nediction: He ſhall, to the eternal purpoſes of Salvation of his Elect, <hi>ſuck the abundance of the Seas, and treaſures bid in the Sand,</hi> when the laſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhall call up thoſe that groan under the Waters, in the houſes of the Giants, and awake them that ſleep in the duſt, <hi>to meet their King in the air, to be with the Lord for ever. 1 Theſſ.</hi> 4. 17. For
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29662:20"/> they indeed are the true riches of the deep, and treaſures of the Sand. Other things, how ſtrong or precious ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſhall yield to the fury of the devouring Element, and the ſame power that brought them out of nothing, ſhall reduce them thither again. But the Bodies of his Saints and their ſeparated duſt, after ſo many Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages and Transformations into the parts of Minerals, Plants, Animals, (which the natural order of things muſt neceſſarily carry them into) ſhall return to their primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſhape, and join again to their primary and predeſtinate forms. And as at the Creation, there was a Separation of that confuſed Maſs into its ſpecies, ſo at the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, there ſhall be a Separation into its diſtinct In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuals. Which great Truth, though perplext with ſome nice curioſities, is more fully explicated unto us. than any other myſtery of our Faith. For ſeeing, as moſt aver, our Salvation conſiſteth in the knowledge of three principal Articles, the Trinity, the Incarnation with its effects and conſequences, and the Reſurrection: Whereas the other two do ſometimes, like the top of <hi>Olympus,</hi> hide themſelves in clouds and darkneſs; yet in this, God diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf more to our ends than his own, has more abundantly explained the point than any other, as an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle moſt relating to our peculiar felicities. For it is well enough known, that having afforded the Ancients but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry obſcure knowledges of the Trinity and Incarnation, he has proclaim'd the Reſurrection by the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by the order of the World, by the publications of the Law <hi>Moſaical,</hi> and more fully by the Evangelical Word. In Nature there is not a flower, a grain, a plant, which preaches not this Homily; and Art, its great Imitatrix, will drive old <hi>Proteus</hi> through a thouſand forms, and when they pleaſe, bring the Prodigal back again home to his Fathers houſe, and fix him there in the embraces of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29662:21"/> his Kindred. In Mundane affairs we ſee Governments are born, and grow up to a certain maturity, and decay and die, and riſe again. The fancies, genius's, fortunes of the dead riſe daily, and fall again to be imitated by after gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. Humane Nature is not capable of more variety than may be ſeen in a few Ages, and therefore Providence has been kind to make our days ſo few, leſt we ſhould too often behold the reſurrection of our own follies and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. <hi>Job</hi> a man before all Letters, all Doctors, all Schools, cries out in a condition the moſt forlorn: <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth, and that he ſhall ſtand at the latter day upon the earth; and though after my skin, worms deſtroy this body, yet in my fleſh ſhall I ſee God, whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf, and mine eyes ſhall behold, and not another. Job</hi> 19. 25, 26, 27. The eternal Truth pronounced himſelf in the Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> Exod. 3. 8. <hi>The God of Abraham, the God of Iſaac, and the God of Jacob;</hi> which himſelf interprets to ſignifie a relation to the Reſurrection, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. In the Evangelical Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, beſides the paſſages of S. <hi>Mat.</hi> S. <hi>Joh.</hi> and S. <hi>Paul,</hi> our Saviour after his Reſurrection converſed forty days upon Earth, and was ſeen of five hundred people at once, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graft this myſtery in the hearts of the Faithful, <hi>That he who is the firſt fruits of the dead will ſanctifie the whole lump.</hi> What Riches, what Pearls may we imagine ſhall then be found in the deep, what Treaſures, what Stones in the Sands to build up the great City, the Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi> Come Lord Jeſus, come quickly; put an end to our ſins and miſeries: Let us enjoy our long expectations, call the Sea to deliver up her dead, and the Earth to ſet free her Priſoners, that we with all them that are departed in the true Faith and fear of thy moſt Holy Name, may have our perfect conſummation and bliſs, both in Body and Soul, by entring into the full fruition of the face and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the moſt adorable Trinity.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:29662:21"/>
            <p>Now as we have given different ſenſes of the words, ſo ſhall we alſo in correſpondence thereunto make our Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications. And firſt to the adventurous Marriners, that they do above all things labour to ſecure the favour and protection of God by an Holy Life. And truly if they ſhall but ſeriouſly conſider the condition thereof, they will find themſelves to lye under many and extraordinary circumſtances, that call them thereto, as,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The wonders and mighty works of God, which they behold, as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks, <hi>They that go down to the Sea in Ships, and occupy their buſineſs in great waters: theſe ſee the works of the Lord, and his wonders in the deep. Pſal.</hi> 107. 23. The ſeveral climates, the different riſing and ſetting of Stars, the divers temperatures of the air, the various com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of all Countries call upon you to praiſe and adore that God, who has diſpoſed all things in ſuch a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful order, and ſo various a manner for the benefit of the whole.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The dangers of Storms, of Rocks, of Shelves, of Sands, make your preſervations miraculous, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently require the greateſt and moſt conſtant Devotions to God for your ſafeties. <hi>Pacuvius</hi> gives us a deſcription of a Tempeſt, ſufficient to allay the courage of the moſt vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, and it is this:</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Inhorreſcit mare,</l>
               <l>Tenebrae conduplicantur, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>The Sea roars with horrour, the darkneſs becomes palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, the blackneſs of the night and ſtorms is a perfect blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Lightning flaſhes through the Clouds, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven trembles with the Thunder: Hail and rain mixt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fall, 'tis hard to ſay in greater plenty or violence; the Winds break out from all points, as if they would not only deſtroy themſelves, but all the World, and the Ocean rages with the Tyde. Now how canſt thou expect
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29662:22"/> to be preſerv'd in ſuch concuſſions and ſtrugglings of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? How canſt thou expect that God ſhould becalm this Tempeſt, aſſwage the fury of the Elements, and ſtretch out his almighty arm to ſave thee in dangers ſo great, if thou daily provokeſt him to anger by thy ſins? No, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him all the days of thy li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e with a pure mind and a chaſte body; and then call upon him in the needful time of trouble, and he ſhall hear thee at large: He ſhall ſtill the raging of the Sea and the ſtorms when they ariſe: He ſhall preſerve thee in a thouſand dangers, ſhall bleſs thee in thy going out and in thy coming in, and bring thee ſafe and proſperouſly into the Haven, where thou wouldſt be, ſo that thou ſhalt rejoice, like <hi>Zabulun,</hi> in thy Ports.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The great Profits and Emoluments which accrue from your employment is a third obligation to your Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Navigation is that which makes the Riches of the World common, and the Merchant may truly be ſaid to <hi>ſuck the abundance of the Sea, and treaſures hid in the Sand.</hi> It is he that mingles the manners and wealth of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons together, that makes good the poverty of one place with the riches of another. Navigation is certainly the greateſt and moſt uſeful Art humane nature was ever maſter of: And whatever there is of Wit, whatever there is of Manners, whatever there is of Riches, whatever there is of Glory, nay, whatever there is of Religion in the World, is in great meaſures owing to the profeſſors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Go then, happy Marriner, fear thy God above all things, and he ſhall bring the Winds out of his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures to fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l thy Sails with gales of Proſperity: Go ſpread thy Religion, thy Laws, thy Manners and Cuſtomes through the Univerſe, and for thy reward reap the harveſt of the River, <hi>ſack the abundance of the deep, and Treaſures hid in the Sands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The great Influence that good example has upon
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29662:22"/> others, calls upon you, eſpecially to a circumſpection in your manners, that no Profaneneſs, Injuſtice or Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance appear in you to the ſcandal of others, or the diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of our Religion. For it is not deep Myſteries, multitude of Laws, or Rational Diſcourſes that will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert Nations. Holy Examples move beyond Precepts, and a converſation void of offence is the moſt effectual Sermon to bring thoſe that are without, into the fold of the Church. In vain therefore, poor Chriſtendom, doſt thou expect the coming in of unbelievers, while they ſee thy wickedneſs at home, &amp; thy profaneneſs abroad. Learn then all, and eſpecially thoſe who view foreign and unconvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Nations, a converſation ſuitable to the doctrine ye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs. Learn that moſt uſeful lecture of our Saviour, <hi>Mat. 5. 16. Let your light ſo ſhine hefore men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your father which is in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond of our Applications ſhall be to us all, but eſpecially to the true <hi>Zabulonites,</hi> that we learn highly to eſteem this Religion we profeſs: A Religion which has overcome ſo many difficulties, been confirm'd by ſuch Miracles, continued by ſuch a wonderful Providence through ſo many Ages: A Religion that glories in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Martyrs, Doctors, Paſtors, Biſhops, and Holy men of the cleareſt Spirits, and greateſt accompliſhments in the World: A Religion that corrects our Errours, that bridles our Paſſions, that ſanctifies our Natures, and gives us the greateſt aſſurances of Gods love to us here, and the moſt infallible revelations of a future and eternal felicity. What if ſome little Spirit blown up with a ſyſtem, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment, a fantaſtick ſong, or ſome giddy <hi>vortex</hi> in his Head, make now and then a fally out againſt this Truth; Is it reaſonable for this, think you, to waver in our Faith, or grow neglective of our duty? No; we have a Law de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver'd by the Word it ſelf, which millions of Martyrs have ſign'd with their Blood, which the beſt of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29662:23"/> profeſſes, the wiſeſt heads of the World have il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrated with the lights of their Writings, and for whoſe defence Heads and Pens, the moſt able, labour daily. But alas! that ancient Zeal which brought the Church to ſo great Glory, and ſo vaſt extent, ſeems much decay'd; and inſtead thereof the Spirit of Atheiſm, Hereſie, Schiſm and luke warmneſs has ſucceeded. So that the ſtate of Religion runs low, the Word of God wants its due belief, the holy Prieſts that reverence that becomes perſons who handle the myſteries of God, the Churches the decency of holy places: And in ſhort, God is defrauded of that Glory which all beings owe to the Majeſty of Heaven, and we all want thoſe comforts of Religion our wiſer and more zealous Anceſtors enjoy'd. The Lord in his due time reſtore that devotion and prudent Zeal which was ſo remarkable in the early Chriſtians, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 2. that many may be provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to the ſame Repentance, Faith, and good works; may <hi>ſuck the abundance of the Seas, and treaſures hid in the Sand, (i. e.)</hi> the ſecrets of the Law, and Myſteries of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us all prepare for that account we muſt give, when Chriſt ſhall ſeize the heritage and benediction of <hi>Zabulun</hi> and <hi>Iſſachar;</hi> when the Sea ſhall give up her dead, and the Earth reſtore the Bodies committed to her charge, that ſo whatever our condition is in this World, our Souls and Bodies may be happy in the next: For <hi>They that be wiſe ſhall outſhine the brightneſs of the Firmament, and they that turn many to righteouſneſs, as the Stars for ever and ever,</hi> Dan. 12. 3. And as S. <hi>John</hi> teaches, 1 <hi>Joh. 3. 2. Beloved, now are we the Sons of God, and it does not yet appear what we ſhall be: but we know that when he ſhall appear, we ſhall be like him: For we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> This is that viſion alone, which can terminate all our deſires in the enjoyment of that eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, whoſe boundleſs goodneſs ſhall fill us with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of himſelf. For in his <hi>preſence is fulneſs of joy, and at his right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi> Pſal. 16. 11.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
